Guide to the Thomas Mann Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Mann collection
1894-1990
YCGL MSS 5
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.5
(20 boxes) + 2 portfolios
The Thomas Mann Collection consists of manuscripts, letters, photographs, and printed materials relating to the life and work of Mann and his wife, Katia.
Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955
Mann, Katia, 1883-1980
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Thomas Mann, 1937; Alfred Vagts, 1938; Agnes E. Meyer, 1957; and others. Purchase from Helen Lowe-Porter, 1957. See further information in Description of the Collection, below.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The roots of Yale's Thomas Mann collection can be traced to Mann's lecture tour of the United States in April, 1937. At that time he first met Joseph Warner Angell and Agnes E. Meyer, who, along with Mann and his English translator, Helen Lowe-Porter, have provided the major blocks of the Thomas Mann material now held by Yale. In 1937, Joseph Angell, then a graduate student at Yale, approached Mann with the plan of establishing an archive of the novelist's life work. Mann's enthusiasm for the proposal grew markedly after their first personal encounter, and he subsequently turned over to Angell some 38 autograph manuscripts for the purpose of founding a collection within the Yale University Library. With Mann's generous support, Joseph Angell supplemented this nucleus with first editions and translations of Mann's works, secondary literature on Mann, and printed sources used by him. By 1938 Yale's president, Charles Seymour, was able to announce the establishment of a Thomas Mann collection; an exhibit was staged in the Rare Book Room, and the collection was officially opened in February with a lecture by Mann. This event stimulated new donations, notably from Mann, now living in exile in the United States; from his American publisher Alfred A. Knopf; from Wilmarth S. Lewis; and from the Yale Library Associates. After he left Yale, Joseph Angell continued to serve as advisor to the collection, overseeing its expansion and the publication of one of its treasures, the rejected pages from the lost autograph manuscript of Der Zauberberg.
On his 1937 lecture tour Mann also met Agnes E. Meyer, who became one of his closest friends and most ardent supporters during his United States exile. Starting in 1957 Agnes Meyer gave to Yale her extensive and important correspondence with Mann, and her notes on their conversations, as well as a few manuscripts by Mann and miscellaneous related materials. Mann's letters to Meyer were edited by Hans R. Vaget and published in 1992 by the Fischer Verlag.
In 1957 Yale purchased the major portion of Helen Lowe-Porter's Thomas Mann papers, including typescripts of her translations of many of the novels, often accompanied by the German typescript prepared for her by Mann. Also included were numerous essays and lectures in English and German versions; a voluminous file of clippings by and about Mann; and some of Helen Lowe- Porter's letters from the novelist. Additional letters from Mann to Helen Lowe-Porter were given to Yale by her daughter, Patricia Lowe Pitzele, in 1969.
The first section of this Register lists Thomas Mann's writings, including translations by Helen Lowe-Porter, in a single alphabetical sequence. Translations, fragments, untitled drafts, and differently titled versions of a single work are collected under the bibliographically accepted title as cited by Hans Buergin in Das Werk Thomas Manns (Frankfurt/Main, 1959). A title appearing on the manuscript is here recorded in capital letters, while a title supplied from Buergin or another source is enclosed in square brackets. In the physical description of the manuscripts, "leaf" designates a single piece of paper, which may contain from 1 to 4 pages of text. The following abbreviations have been used: TM - Thomas Mann KM - Katia Mann HLP - Helen Lowe-Porter AEM - Agnes E. Meyer JWA - Joseph Warner Angell TLS - Typed letter, signed TL - Typed letter ALS - Autograph letter, signed APCS - Autograph post card, signed TPCS - Typed post card, signed ACS - Autograph card, signed ANS - Autograph note, signed tel. - telegram Christa Sammons, May 1980
Authors, German -- Archives; Mann, Katia, 1883-1980; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955
- Thomas Mann. Writings, 1926-45; Series I; 5; (12 boxes)
  - 1. [Achtung, Europa] EUROPE, TAKE CARE! Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP; 17 leaves (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2. ADDRESS DELIVERED AT A BOOK AND AUTHOR LUNCHEON... NOVEMBER 9, 1938 Typescript (original) with many corrections and additions by TM and some corrections by HLP; 8 numbered leaves Another version, typescript (original); 4 leaves (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 3. [Anna Karenina] EINLEITUNG ZU "ANNA KARENINA" Typescript (carbon), with a few minor corrections by TM, dated Noordwijk aan Zee, Juli 1939; 25 numbered leaves, with added title page (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 4. [Ansprache in Princeton] MR. PRESIDENT, GENTLEMAN Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP; 7 numbered leaves (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 5. [Das Bild der Mutter] Autograph manuscript with corrections; 4 numbered leaves (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 6. [Brief an den Verteidiger L. Hatvanys] Autograph manuscript with corrections; 7 numbered leaves (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 7. BRIEF AN DEN WARSCHAUER P.E.N. CLUB Autograph manuscript with corrections, dated 26 V 1930; 4 numbered leaves (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 8. BRIEF AN DR. SEIPEL Autograph manuscript with corrections; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 9. [Brief an Stephen Hudson] Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions; 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 10. BRIEF UeBER DIE SCHWEIZ Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, dated Muenchen den 15 IX 23; 3 folded leaves (12 pages of text) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 11. [Brief ueber nationale und internationale Kunst] Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, dated Feldafing, 11 VI 22; 9 numbered leaves (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 12. [Ein Briefwechsel] Obenauer, Karl Justus TLS to Thomas Mann, revoking his honorary doctorate from the Universitaet Bonn, 1936 Dec. 19, Bonn; 1 leaf, with envelope Draft of TM's reply, autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, dated Kuesnacht, Neujahr 1936/37; 11 leaves numbered 1-10 (4a added) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 13. [Bruder Hitler] TAGEBUCHBLAeTTER. ANFANG APRIL 1938, BEVERLY HILLS, CALIFORNIEN Typescript (original) with corrections by TM; 14 numbered leaves A BROTHER -- THIS MAN IS MY BROTHER Manuscript in the hand of HLP with her corrections; 28 leaves DER BRUDER Page proof from Achtung, Europa! with a few autograph corrections by TM; pages 167-177 with Table of Contents and half-title. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 14. [Buddenbrooks] THOMAS B. Autograph notes, 1 leaf; With typed English translation, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 15. [Buddenbrooks. Musik des Lebens] PREFACE TO THE RECORDED EDITION OF BUDDENBROOKS Typescript (carbon); 3 numbered leaves (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 16. [Deutsche Ansprache] AN APPEAL TO REASON... A SPEECH DELIVERED IN BERLIN ON OCTOBER 17th, 1930 Galley proof with a few corrections by HLP; 6 sheets (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 17. [Deutsche Hoerer, Dezember 1940] Typescript (original) with a few corrections by TM; 4 numbered leaves English translation by HLP, Typescript (original) heavily corrected by HLP; 4 leaves (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 18. [Deutsche Hoerer, Januar 1941] BOTSCHAFT NACH DEUTSCHLAND II Typescript (original) with corrections and deletions by TM; 3 numbered leaves 19. [Deutsche Hoerer, Mai 1941] BOTSCHAFT NACH DEUTSCHLAND I Typescript (original) with corrections and deletions by TM; 3 numbered leaves (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 20. [Deutsche Hoerer] 1. MAI 1944 Typescript (original); 3 numbered leaves English translation, typescript (carbon) with corrections by HLP; 3 numbered leaves (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 21. DIESER FRIEDE Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, signed and dated Princeton, N.J., Mitte Oktober 1938; 22 numbered leaves Typescript (carbon) with corrections by TM; 19 numbered leaves (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 22. DOKTOR FAUSTUS Typescript (original) with corrections and deletions by TM 3 preliminary leaves, 952 leaves numbered 1-952 (112a, 138a added; 145-149 deleted with 1 page substituted; 246a, 296a, 310a added; 348-349 deleted; 350a added; 351, 355 deleted; 413a added; 592 deleted with 1 page numbered 591-592a substituted; 595, 596 deleted; 608a, 679a, 695a added; 708 deleted; 770a added; 779-782 deleted with 1 page substituted; 857a, 857b, 857c added.) (Box 1, Folder 21-25)
  - 22. DOCTOR FAUSTUS Typescript (original) with corrections and deletions by TM (cont.) (Box 2, Folder 26-30)
  - 23. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP] DOCTOR FAUSTUS Typescript (original) heavily corrected throughout by HLP and others; 1179 leaves numbered 1-1091, 1-62, 1-17 (in the first count, 301, 302 repeated; 326 omitted; 466a added; 469-531 irregularly numbered resulting in 9 extra pages; 552, 788 omitted) With numerous extra, unnumbered small sheets inserted, containing notes and corrections. (Box 2, Folder 31-36)
  - 23. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP] DOCTOR FAUSTUS Typescript (original) heavily corrected throughout by HLP and others (cont.) (Box 3, Folder 37-42)
  - 24. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP] DOCTOR FAUSTUS Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP and a copy editor. The final draft of the translation. 732 leaves numbered 1-731 (259a added) (Box 3, Folder 43-47)
  - 24. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP] DOCTOR FAUSTUS Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP and a copy editor. The final draft of the translation. (cont.) (Box 4, Folder 48-49)
  - 25. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP] DOCTOR FAUSTUS Typescript (carbon) with corrections by HLP, carbon copy of register number 24, listed above; 3 preliminary leaves, 730 numbered leaves (Box 4, Folder 50-54)
  - 26. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP] PART OF CHAP. XII Typescript (original); 5 leaves numbered 182-188 (183-84 omitted) Carbon copy of the same text, with some German written between the lines. Marked "No use." 5 leaves, numbered as the original. (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - 27. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP] PART OF CHAP. XV [Adrian's letter] Typescript (original) with manuscript corrections in an unknown hand; 13 leaves numbered 257-267 Copy of the same text in German, typescript (original); 15 leaves numbered 248-257 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - 28. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP] PART OF CHAP. XVI [Adrian's letter] Typescript (original) with notes and corrections by HLP and in another hand; 16 leaves numbered 276-287 Copy of the same text in German with manuscript notes; 10 leaves numbered 265-274 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - 29. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP] CHAPTER XXV [Draft of Zeitblom's transcript of Adrian's manuscript] Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP; 64 leaves numbered 467-530 Another version of the same passage, typescript (original) with corrections and notes by HLP and in another hand; 75 leaves numbered 466-531 Complete copy of Chapter XXV in German, typescript (original) with underlining and notes by HLP and in another hand; 50 leaves numbered 421-472 (lacks page 423 and a final page with the duplicate number 472) Carbon copy of the German text of Chapter XXV listed directly above; 52 leaves numbered 421-472 (Box 4, Folder 58-59)
  - 30. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP. Miscellaneous drafts of passages relating to music, from Chapters IV-XVI] Typescripts (originals) in English and German, with corrections to the English texts in an unknown hand. The corrections affect chiefly the musical terminology. 64 leaves of nonconsecutive drafts (Box 5, Folder 60-64)
  - 31. [Doktor Faustus. English translation by HLP. Miscellaneous drafts of passages relating to music] Typescripts in English only, with corrections and notes by HLP and in an unknown hand; 30 leaves of nonconsecutive drafts (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - 32. [Dostojewski--mit Massen] Typescript (carbon) with a few corrections, dated: Pacif. Palisades, Calif. Juli 1945; 26 numbered leaves (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - 33. [Einfuehrung in den Zauberberg fuer Studenten der Universitaet Princeton. English translation by HLP] LECTURE ON THE ZAUBERBERG Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP; 17 leaves (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - 34. DIE EINHEIT DES MENSCHENGEISTES Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, signed; 4 numbered leaves (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - 35. DER ERWAeHLTE Typescript (original) with corrections, 342 numbered leaves, with 2 extra typed leaves at the end and one list of page numbers (not in TM's hand) inserted (Box 5, Folder 69-72)
  - 36. [Der Erwaehlte. English translation by HLP] THE HOLY SINNER Typescript (original) with corrections by a copyeditor and a few corrections by HLP; 348 leaves numbered 1-347 (57a inserted) (Box 5, Folder 73-76)
  - 37. [Essays of Three Decades] Typescript (carbon) with corrections by HLP. The essays are paged individually as follows: [Preliminary matter, notes, errata, and appendix], 28 nonconsecutive leaves; CHAMISSO, 1 preliminary leaf, 27 numbered leaves, with an extra draft of the last two paragraphs, 1 leaf; AMPHITRYON, 1 preliminary leaf, 62 numbered leaves; GOETHE AS REPRESENTATIVE OF THE BOURGEOIS AGE OF GERMAN CULTURE, 1 preliminary leaf, 41 numbered leaves; GOETHE'S CAREER AS A MAN OF LETTERS, 1 preliminary leaf, 38 numbered leaves; ANNA KARENINA, 1 preliminary leaf, 20 numbered leaves; SCHOPENHAUER, 1 preliminary leaf, 65 numbered leaves; RICHARD WAGNER AND THE RING, 1 preliminary leaf, 28 numbered leaves; PLATEN, 1 preliminary leaf, 17 numbered leaves; THEODOR STORM, l preliminary leaf, 24 numbered leaves; THE OLD FONTANE, 1 preliminary leaf, 32 numbered leaves; VOYAGE WITH DON QUIXOTE, 1 preliminary leaf, 53 numbered leaves; GOETHE'S FAUST, 1 preliminary leaf, 53 numbered leaves. (Box 6, Folder 77-89)
  - Note: The essays "Goethe and Tolstoy," "Lessing," "The Suffering and Greatness of Richard Wagner," and "Freud and the Future" are not present in this typescript.
  - 38. [Franklin Roosevelt, English translation by HLP] GOODNESS AND POWER Typescript (original) with a few corrections by HLP; 4 numbered leaves (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - 39. FREUD UND DIE ZUKUNFT. VORTRAG, GEHALTEN IN WIEN AM 8. MAI 1936 ZUR FEIER VON SIGMUND FREUDS 80. GEBURTSTAG Typescript (original) with a few corrections and deletions, dated 3.V.36. Title page in TM's hand. 1 preliminary leaf, 34 leaves numbered 1-33 (15 repeated in numbering) Carbon copy of the same typescript, with a few corrections but without the title page; 34 leaves numbered 1-33 (15 repeated) (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - 40. FREUD UND DIE ZUKUNFT [A different version, partly identical with the essay of this title, partly identical with the essay "Die Stellung Freuds in der modernen Geistesgeschichte."] Typescript (original) with a few corrections and notes by TM; 28 leaves numbered 1-27 (7 repeated in numbering) Partial English translation by HLP] FREUD AND THE FUTURE Typescript (original) with a few corrections and notes by HLP; 26 numbered leaves (Box 6, Folder 92-93)
  - 41. [Geist und Wesen der deutschen Republik] GEDENKREDE AUF RATHENAU Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions; 9 numbered leaves (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - 42. [Die geistige Situation des Schriftstellers in unserer Zeit] LIEBE ROTARIAR, MEINE HERREN Autograph manuscript with a few corrections, dated: Nidden, August 30; 9 numbered leaves (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - 43. [Geleitwort. In: Erika Mann, Zehn Millionen Kinder] Typescript (carbon), dated: New York 7. Mai 38; 5 numbered leaves [English translation by HLP] PREFACE TO ERIKA MANN'S BOOK Typescript (carbon), dated; New York, May seventh, 1938; 6 leaves (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - 44. [German Letter] [Untitled German original beginning: Unser Theater... ach, lassen Sie mich ueber unser Theater nicht viele Worte machen!] Autograph manuscript with corrections, dated: Muenchen, Juni 1923; 11 numbered leaves (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - 45. [Die Geschichten Jaakobs] Autograph manuscript with many corrections, deletions, and insertions: 487 leaves numbered 1-488 (6a, 6b, 6c, 71a, 71b, 71c, 117a added; 236-243 omitted in numbering). With one leaf of autograph sketches of Egyptian motifs. (Box 6, Folder 98-113)
  - 46. [Das Gesetz. English translation by HLP] THE TABLES OF THE LAW Typescript (carbon) with corrections by HLP; 65 numbered leaves (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - 46a. GOETHE Typescript (original) with corrections, not in TM's hand; 10 numbered leaves An address, not identical with any of Mann's major printed Goethe essays. (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - 47. [Goethe und Tolstoi] NOTIZEN ZU "GOETHE UND TOLSTOI" Autograph manuscript; 29 folded leaves (100 pages of text) and wrapper with the title in TM's hand. (Published by Univ. of Alabama Press, edited by Clayton Koelb, 1984) (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - 48. [Goethes Werther] GOETHE'S "WERTHER." LECTURE FOR PRINCETON STUDENTS (text in German) Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, signed; 15 numbered leaves (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - 49. [In Memoriam Hugo von Hofmannsthal] IN MEMORIAM NEKROLOG HOFMANNSTHAL. Autograph manuscript with corrections, dated: 17./18. VII. 29; 7 leaves (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - 50. [In my Defense] QUOTATIONS (text in German) Typescript (original) with a few corrections, dated: 2. Juli 1944; 7 numbered leaves (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - 51. JOSEPH DER ERNAeHRER Typescript (original) with some corrections by TM and a few notations by HLP; 2 preliminary leaves (chapter plan), 509 leaves numbered 1-510 (207 repeated in numbering, 258 omitted, 348 repeated, 349 omitted, 465-66 omitted, 480a added, 501 repeated, 502 omitted) (Box 7, Folder 120-124)
  - 52. [Joseph der Ernaehrer] Typescript (carbon) with corrections in an unknown hand. Carbon copy of the typescript listed above under number 51; 508 leaves numbered 1-510 (76 missing, 207 repeated, 258 omitted, 348 repeated, 349 omitted, 465-66 omitted, 480a added, 501 repeated, 502 omitted) (Box 7, Folder 125-129)
  - 53. [Joseph der Ernaehrer. English translation by HLP] JOSEPH THE PROVIDER Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP and by a copyeditor; 1 preliminary leaf, 610 leaves numbered 1-606 (84a, 102a, 133a added, 326 repeated in numbering) (Box 8, Folder 130-135)
  - 54. [Joseph der Ernaehrer. English translation by HLP. Joseph the Provider] Typescript (chiefly carbon) with corrections by HLP and by a copyeditor and with a note on page 1 in TM's hand. Carbon copy of the typescript listed above under no. 53 with these exceptions: pages 1-29 are the original typescript of another typing; and pages 1-6, fourth count ("Israel Stands before Pharoh") is an original typescript not present in register number 53. 616 leaves numbered 1-286; 1-47; 333-547; 1-6; 548-606 (84a, 102a added, 133 repeated in numbering) (Box 8, Folder 136-141)
  - 55. [Joseph in Aegypten. English translation by HLP. Joseph in Egypt] Typescript (original) with corrections and notes by a copyeditor; 929 leaves numbered 1-928 (196a added) (Box 9, Folder 142-147)
  - 56. [The Joseph Novels] JOSEPH AND HIS BRETHREN. A LECTURE DELIVERED IN THE LIBRARY OF CONGRESS NOVEMBER 17th, 1942 Photostat of a typescript with some corrections and the title in TM's hand. 3 copies: 2 positive, 1 negative. Original is at the Library of Congress; 23 leaves numbered 1-22 (14a inserted) (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - 57. [Der junge Joseph] Autograph manuscript with many corrections, deletions, and insertions by TM; 362 leaves numbered 489-846 (686a, 712a, 717a, and 731a added). Leaves 574-581 are present in typescript only and are unnumbered. Completes the manuscript listed above under number 45. (Box 10, Folder 149-160)
  - 58. [Koenigliche Hoheit] [Preface to Royal Highness] Typescript (carbon) with corrections by HLP, dated: Noordwijk aan Zee, Holland. July 1939; 10 leaves numbered 1-9 (4 repeated in numbering) (Box 10, Folder 161)
  - 59. KOSMOPOLITISMUS Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions; 9 numbered leaves. First printed with the title: Was verdanken Sie der kosmopolitischen Idee? (Box 10, Folder 162)
  - 60. KULTUR UND SOZIALISMUS Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions; 14 numbered leaves (Box 10, Folder 163)
  - 61. [Die Kunst des Romans] Typescript (original) with a few corrections by TM and a few notes by HLP; 18 numbered leaves (Box 10, Folder 164)
  - 62. [Leiden und Groesse Richard Wagners] RICHARD WAGNER-- VORTRAG Typescript (original) with corrections and deletions, dated 29.I.33; 36 numbered leaves and paper wrapper with the title in TM's hand (Box 10, Folder 165)
  - 63. [Letter. In: Erika and Klaus Mann, Escape to Life] MY DEAR CHILDREN Typescript (original); 3 leaves (Box 10, Folder 166)
  - 64. LITTLE GRANDMA' (text in German) Typescript (original) with corrections by TM, dated: October 1941 by HLP; 10 numbered leaves (Box 10, Folder 167)
  - 65. LOTTE IN WEIMAR. 1. & 3. KAPITEL Printed version from Mass und Wert I: 1, 2, with notes and marginalia by HLP (Box 10, Folder 168)
  - 66. LUeBECK ALS GEISTIGE LEBENSFORM Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, dated: Arosa, Pfingsten 1926; 26 numbered leaves (Box 10, Folder 169)
  - 67. MASS UND WERTH Autograph manuscript with many corrections and deletions; 22 leaves in the original paper wrapper with TM's handwritten dedication to AEM, dated New York den 21. Febr 1938; in a green leather case stamped with gold "MASS UND WERT" Typescript original with a few corrections by TM; 17 numbered leaves (Box 10, Folder 170-171)
  - 68. [Max Liebermann zum 80. Geburtstag] LIEBERMANN Autograph manuscript with a few corrections; 4 numbered leaves (Box 10, Folder 172)
  - 69. [Meerfahrt mit Don Quixote. English translation by HLP] VOYAGE WITH DON QUIXOTE Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP; 13 numbered leaves (fragment) Another version of the translation Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP, dated: 1934; 59 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 173)
  - 70. [En Mester i produktiv Kritik] POLITIKEN, KOPENHAGEN Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, signed, and dated: Ettal, Oberbayern den 10. II. 27; 3 leaves. Essay on the death of G. Brandes, which apparently did not appear in the original German version during TMs lifetime. (Box 11, Folder 174)
  - 71. NIEMOELLER (text in German) Typescript (original) with minor corrections, not in TM's hand, dated: Pacific Palisades 31 July 41; 8 leaves numbered 1-7 (5a added) (Box 11, Folder 175)
  - 72. [Order of the Day] VORWORT Typescript (original) with a few corrections by TM, dated: Pacific Palisades, 11. Juni 1942; 14 numbered leaves [English translation of the last paragraph of the "Vorwort"] Autograph manuscript in TM's hand; 1 leaf [English translation of the "Vorwort" by HLP] FOREWARD; Autograph manuscript in HLP's hand with her corrections; 12 leaves (24 pages of text) [List of suggested improvements to the English translation of the essays] Typescript (carbon), initialed by Raymond A. Preston; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 176-177)
  - 73. "DIE PFEFFERMUeHLE" Typescript (original); 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 178)
  - 74. [Phi Beta Kappa Speech at Swarthmore] (Original German text, untitled - authorship attributed to Mann's secretary, Hans Meisel) Typescript (original) with a few corrections, not in TM's hand; 11 numbered leaves [English translation by HLP] PHI BETA KAPPA SPEECH AT SWARTHMORE, JUNE 1940 Typescript (original); 5 leaves (Box 11, Folder 179)
  - 75. [Rede, gehalten beim Festessen des PEN-Clubs in Warshau] REDE IM WARSHAUER P.E.N. CLUB Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions; 7 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 180)
  - 76. REDE IN KOPENHAGEN Autograph manuscript with corrections; 5 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 181)